<item>
	<title>Caffeinism</title>
	<link>http://chexov.posterous.com/caffeinism</link>
	<pubDate>Thu Nov 04 14:08:00 -0700 2010</pubDate>
	
	<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anton Checkhov]]></dc:creator>
	
	

	<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

	<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://chexov.posterous.com/caffeinism</guid>
	<description></description>
	<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="post-title entry-title" style="font-size: 22px; color: #000000;"><span style="font-size: 15px;">The Addictive Properties of Caffeine</span></h3>
<div class="post-body entry-content">
<p>If you have difficulty relating to people or dealing with life before you have had your morning cup of coffee, you may well be addicted to caffeine-the condition now referred to as "caffeinism". Caffeine is an addictive substance that produces a well-defined abstinence syndrome when abruptly discontinued: headache, irritability, lethargy, drowsiness, fatigue, depression and even nausea in some people.</p>
<p>Recent research shows that even people who consume relatively small amounts of caffeine (e.g., two cups of coffee daily) may experience such severe withdrawal symptoms that they quickly return to their brew. Indeed, relapse is a hallmark of addiction; it refers to the tendency to return to the drug after a period of abstinence. This is certainly a common experience with people who attempt to withdraw from caffeine-which begs the question: is it even necessary to give up caffeine? As with many issues, the answer is: "it depends".</p>
<h3>So What If I Use Caffeine?</h3>
<p>The use of caffeinated beverages is simply a part of society. While studies show that caffeine adds a subjective flavor value to beverages, the fact of the matter is that taste is only part of the reason people use caffeine. Most people who use caffeine regularly will admit that its mild stimulant properties are a boon to their energy level, mood and productivity. So what's wrong with that? Probably nothing, provided your caffeine use causes no problems for you.</p>
<p>People vary in their sensitivity to the acute effects of caffeine. Some people experience the characteristic signs of over-stimulation with minimal doses: jitteriness, nervousness, sleeplessness, heart palpitations and irritability. Others can consume copious amounts of caffeine with seemingly no negative effects whatsoever. Other potential problems from caffeine include muscle tension, headaches, ringing in the ears (tinnitus) and stomach irritation.</p>
<p>Caffeine is a diuretic-a drug that increases the output of urine-so using caffeinated beverages as the only source of fluid could lead to dehydration. A sign of early dehydration is a sensation of warmth, often in the hands and feet, that is not explained by room temperature or excess clothing. (Drinking water will relieve this in short order.)</p>
<p>If you experience no negative effects from your caffeine use, it may not be necessary to cut down or eliminate it from your diet at all. Perhaps the issue in deciding this question should be whether your caffeine use causes any long- term effects-and that probably depends on how much and how often you use it.</p>
<h3>Long-Term Effects of Caffeine</h3>
<p>Most of the "caffeine research" is actually coffee research. And since coffee contains numerous substances besides caffeine, it is uncertain whether the results of coffee research can be attributed solely to caffeine. Nevertheless, the literature tends to apply conclusions about coffee research to caffeine use in general.</p>
<p>In the last decade, many articles have claimed that there is a link between coffee and a variety of cancers-bladder, pancreas, colon, ovary and kidney to name a few. But evaluation of 16,000 men and women observed from 1967 to 1979 found no correlation between coffee consumption and cancer at any body site. In fact, some studies have actually suggested that caffeine may protect against some cancers.</p>
<p>Although most obstetricians advise their pregnant patients to abstain from caffeine or limit consumption to less than 200 mg. per day, there is no evidence linking birth defects with caffeine, nor is it known to cause hyperactivity in children. The greatest harm to coffee's reputation in recent years has come from research on heart disease. Several studies have shown that daily consumption of three to five cups of coffee significantly increases blood cholesterol levels (high blood cholesterol is a major risk factor for coronary artery disease).</p>
<p>Moreover, a Norwegian study of 14,500 men and women showed that heavy coffee drinkers with high blood cholesterol who abstained from coffee lowered their cholesterol levels an average of 13 percent. But further analysis of the data showed that the coffee drinkers tended to smoke, consume more fats and lead sedentary lives- all significant contributors to high blood cholesterol, therefore, the conclusions are believed to be invalid.</p>
<p>Experts do not question that caffeine can increase heart rate, blood pressure and cause irregular heart beat. However, these effects are minimal and are of no consequence in people who have no symptoms of heart or artery disease.</p>
<p>Much has been written in popular and professional literature about caffeine and breast disorders in women. Caffeine is not suspected of causing breast cancer, but it clearly causes breast swelling and associated tenderness. If this is a problem for you, cutting down or eliminating caffeine may be the best choice. There appears to be no justification for the claim that caffeine causes fibrocystic breast condition (benign cysts in the breasts that may be tender).</p>
<p>Caffeine stimulates the production of stomach acids and thus should not be used by people who have ulcers and limited by people who are prone to stomach irritation. In fact, heavy consumption of caffeinated beverages may actually cause ulcers. Caffeine use may be something you want to monitor if you are trying to lose weight, since it causes release of fats into the blood stream, which set up an insulin reaction that can result in low blood sugar. The primary implication of this is that low blood sugar is a signal to eat.</p>
<p>If you find that caffeine use is associated with a need to eat unscheduled meals during a weight-loss program, then evaluate whether eliminating it is something you want to do. The basic answer to the question, "is caffeine bad for me?" is that it's okay for healthy people in moderation. Moderation is always tricky to define, but studies on the ill effects of caffeine found that 200-300 mg daily produces no negative long-term effects. (See the equivalency chart to find out how much caffeine your beverage has relative to that.)</p>
<p>In the final analysis, your use of caffeine is a personal choice and its risk to your health should be considered in light of all other health risks you experience. And like all other choices you make about your health, it's good to have some facts on which to base decisions.</p>
<h3>Caffeine Source</h3>
<p>Caffeine is found not only in coffee, tea, chocolate and colas, but also in other soft drinks such as Mountain Dew " and in some over-the-counter (OTC) drugs such as Anacin". Generally speaking, coffee contains more caffeine than tea, but that may depend on how long the tea was steeped; green teas have less caffeine than black teas. The chart on the next page provides a comparison of the caffeine content of various products.</p>
<h3>Caffeine Content</h3>
<h4>Beverages</h4>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<table class="styletable">
 
<tr>
<th>Beverge</th><th>Beverage Amount</th><th>Caffeine Amount (mg)</th>
</tr>
 

<tr>
<td>Coffee (drip)</td>
<td>5 oz.</td>
<td>110 - 150</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Coffee (perk)</td>
<td>5 oz.</td>
<td>60 - 125</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Coffee (instant)</td>
<td>5 oz.</td>
<td>40 - 105</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Coffee (decaf)</td>
<td>5 oz.</td>
<td>2 - 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tea (5 min. deep)</td>
<td>5 oz.</td>
<td>40 -100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tea (3 min. deep)</td>
<td>5 oz.</td>
<td>20 - 50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hot cocoa</td>
<td>5 oz.</td>
<td>2 - 10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cola (diet/regular)</td>
<td>12 oz.</td>
<td>36 - 49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dr. Pepper/Mr. Pibb</td>
<td>12 oz.</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Orange soda</td>
<td>12 oz.</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mountain Dew</td>
<td>12 oz.</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>

</table>
<p><span style="font-family: Georgia, serif; font-size: 16px;"> </span></p>
<div class="post-body entry-content">
<p>Non-caffeinated drinks include: 7-Up, Fresca, Fanta products, Squirt, Teem, Canada Dry Ginger Ale and Hires Root Beer</p>
<h4>Food</h4>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<table class="styletable">
 
<tr>
<th>Foods</th><th>Food Amount</th><th>Caffeine Amount (mg)</th>
</tr>
 

<tr>
<td>Milk chocolate</td>
<td>1 oz.</td>
<td>1 - 15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bittersweet chocolate</td>
<td>1 oz.</td>
<td>5 - 35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chocolate cake</td>
<td>1 average slice</td>
<td>20 - 30</td>
</tr>

</table>
<p><span style="font-family: Georgia, serif; font-size: 16px;"> </span></p>
<div class="post-body entry-content">
<h4>Over-the-Counter Drugs</h4>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<table class="styletable">
 
<tr>
<th>Medication</th><th>Dosage</th><th>Caffeine Amount (mg)</th>
</tr>
 

<tr>
<td>Anacin</td>
<td>2 tablets</td>
<td>64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Empirin</td>
<td>2 tablets</td>
<td>64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Midol</td>
<td>2 tablets</td>
<td>64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Excedrin</td>
<td>2 tablets</td>
<td>130</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NoDoz</td>
<td>2 tablets</td>
<td>200</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aqua-Ban (diuretic)</td>
<td>2 tablets</td>
<td>200</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dexatrim</td>
<td>1 capsule</td>
<td>200</td>
</tr>

</table>
<p><span style="font-family: Georgia, serif; font-size: 16px;"> </span></p>
<div class="post-body entry-content">
<h3>Cutting Down Or Eliminating Caffeine</h3>
<p>If you choose to cut down or eliminate caffeine, do it gradually over a period of about a week. You can do it by:</p>
<ul>
<li>reducing the number of uses each day</li>
<li>decreasing the amount in each use</li>
<li>decreasing the caffeine content of each use. For example, if you get your cola from a dispenser, fill your cup half with decaffeinated and half with regular. You may discover after cutting down that your negative effects remit, making eliminating caffeine unnecessary.</li>
</ul>
<p>On the other hand, a "hardcore" caffeine addict may not be able to cut down permanently; they often gradually work their way back to the prior level of use. If this happens to you, it may be time to make another decision: whether to cut caffeine out altogether. Again, the ultimate choice will depend on what kind, if any, problems you experience from caffeine.</p>
<h3>What About Decaffeinated Coffee?</h3>
<p>Perhaps you heard that decaffeinated coffee is no better for you than the "real" thing. That really depends on whether the "real thing" causes you problems in the first place. If stomach problems caused you to give up your preferred brew, decaf will not treat you any better. The acid and other chemicals in decaf create the same gastric environment as regular coffee.</p>
<p>One worry about decaffeinated coffee has been put to rest, however. It was once thought to be carcinogenic because of the solvent (methylene chloride) used to extract caffeine from some brands. This chemical was shown to cause cancer in laboratory animals when inhaled, but not when consumed.</p>
<p>Moreover, the amount of solvent remaining in the bean after decaffeination is so minimal as to be of little concern. But there are plenty of water-processed decaffeinated coffees available if this issue is of concern to you, although the extra expense of them probably offers no appreciable health advantages.</p>
<p>A Stanford University study that showed decaffeinated coffee to raise LDL ("bad") cholesterol in the blood was found to be flawed. The increase in the 181 volunteers (a small sample of just men) was only 5 mg per deciliter of blood-a statistically insignificant increase. Moreover, the coffees used by each group (caf and decaf) were made from different beans, which could have accounted for this minute difference.</p>
<p>Consider the known facts relative to caffeine and make good choices for yourself.</p>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]></content:encoded>
	<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The Addictive Properties of Caffeine If you have difficulty relating to people or dealing with life before you have had your morning cup of coffee, you may well be addicted to caffeine-the condition now referred to as "caffeinism". Caffeine is an ...]]></excerpt:encoded>	

	<wp:post_date>Thu Nov 04 14:08:00 -0700 2010</wp:post_date>
	<wp:post_date_gmt>%= display_date %></wp:post_date_gmt>
	<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
	<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
	<wp:post_name>caffeinism</wp:post_name>
	<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
	<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
	<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
	<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
	<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
	<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>

	
</item>
